<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>
<!-- <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?> -->
<rfc
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  category="info"
  docName="draft-poisonlicious-00"
  ipr="trust200902"
  obsoletes=""
  updates=""
  submissionType="IETF"
  xml:lang="en"
  version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Poisonlicious">Synchronizing caches of DNS resolvers</title>

    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-poisonlicious-00"/>
   
    <author fullname="Stéphane Bortzmeyer" initials="S." surname="Bortzmeyer">
      
      <organization>Afnic</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>7 avenue du 8 mai 1945</street>
          <city>Guyancourt</city>
          <code>78280</code>
          <country>FR</country>
          <!-- Uses two letter country code -->
        </postal>        
        <email>bortzmeyer+ietf@nic.fr</email>  
        <uri>https://www.afnic.fr/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
   
    <date year="2025"/>

    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <keyword>DNS DNSSEC optimization caching</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>Network of cooperating and mutually trusting DNS resolvers
      could benefit from cache sharing, where one resolver would
      distribute the result of a resolution to other resolvers. This
      document standardizes a protocol to do so.</t>
    </abstract>
 
  </front>

  <middle>
    
    <section>
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>When an organisation operates a big network of DNS resolvers
      <xref target="RFC1034"/> <xref target="RFC1035"/>, for
      instance for an important public resolver <xref
      target="RFC9499"/> (section 6), it may be a performance
      improvment to distribute the result of the resolution process
      between the resolvers. This document standardizes how to to do
      so, using blockchains (just kidding) and unicast messages to a
      set of pre-configured peers.
      </t>
      <t>TODO data from Quad9 to show that there is a caching
      improvment to expect. Measuring the efficiency of caching
      optimizations is hard!</t>
      
      <section>
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
          "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
          RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
          interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
          <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in
          all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>

      <section>
	<name>Terminology</name>
        <dl newline="true">
        <dt>Network of resolvers (TODO or resolver set?)</dt>
        <dd>A set of resolvers working together under the same administration</dd>
        <dt>Peer (or peer resolver)</dt>
        <dd>One of the other resolvers in the network</dd>
        <dt>Originating resolver</dt>
        <dd>A resolver sending data to its peers in the network</dd>
        <dt>Receiving resolver (or receiving peer)</dt>
        <dd>A resolver receiving data from one of its peers in the network</dd>
        <dt>Resolver</dt>
        <dd>As used in <xref target="RFC9499"/> section 6</dd>
      </dl>
      </section>
      
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>The protocol</name>
      <t>When completing a successful DNS resolution, the resolver
      transmits a DNS message (with the Q/R bit set, since it is a
      response) to the pre-configured peers, authenticating with TSIG
      <xref target="RFC8945"/>. TODO SIG0? DoT? No acknowledgment is
      sent or expected.</t>
      <t>The resolver must send
      only data that it is sure of (for instance by DNSSEC valitaion
      or because it came with the AA bit from the queried
      server). Since all of the netwok of resolvers are in the same
      organizational domain, they MUST agree on the same policy for
      this assessment.</t>
      <t>Messages of this protocol are distinguished from other DNS
      messages by the TSIG key they use (which must therefore be
      specific to this protocol). TODO or by a dedicated port?</t>
      <t>This message MAY be the message received by the resolver from
      the authoritative name servers or it MAY be a new message with
      data composed from data already obtained by the resolver. TODO
      privacy risks when sending the question section? Force its elision?</t>
      <t>The EDNS section MUST be a new one, created to fit the needs
      of successful transmission to the peer. TODO what about ECS?</t>
      <t>Each peer then MAY store the data in
      its cache. The peer is not supposed to do DNSSEC validation
      (there is not always all the necessary data in the
      message). TODO cache only what is in the Answer section? See
      above about assessing the trustiness of the data.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="IANA">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>None. [RFC-Editor: you may delete this section]</t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="Security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>The integrity and authenticity of the cached data is of
      course critical. DNSSEC would help but it is not yet universally
      deployed and, moreover, the peer resolvers should not have to
      redo the validation. So, trust between the peer resolvers is
      expected. One way to do so is to have all of them under the same
      organisational authority, as mandated here.</t>
      <t>The channel between peers must be protected, preferrably with
      cryptography (currently, TSIG is mandatory).</t>
      <t>Encryption is less important than authentication since we
      transmit only public data. Nevertheless, it is better to be sure
      that the channel between the peers is not open to snooping.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="Operation">
      <name>Operational Considerations</name>
      <t>It is reminded that all resolvers in the network need to trust
      each other, probably being in the same administrative
      domain. This specification is not meant to be deployed between
      unrelated resolvers.</t>
      <t>The netwok of peer resolvers have to be configured
      out-of-band before. The way to do it is out-of-scope for this specification.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="related-future">
      <name>Related and future work</name>
      <section>
	<name>Related work</name>
	<t><xref target="I-D.hl-dnsop-cache-filling"/> describes a
	mechanism to fill DNS caches with data. The format is, like in
	this document, standard DNS as ween on the wire.</t>
      </section>
      <section>
      <name>Future work</name>
      <section>
	<name>Negative answers</name>
	<t>TODO What to do about them? Transmit them? (Be careful of
	the risk of overloading receving peers for instance when there
	is a dictionary attack.) Can a receiving peer use <xref
	target="RFC8020"/> an/or <xref target="RFC8198"/> to
	synthetize negative answers since it did not validate data itself?</t>
      </section>
      <section>
	<name>Transport of messages</name>
         <t>It may be interesting to replace the unicasts messages by
         multicast (the issues of multicast on the public Internet do
	 no apply here since we envision work under only one
	 organisation). For instance, if we use DoT for the transport
	 of messages and if there are 1,000 servers, having a full
	 mesh of DoT connections may be too much.</t>
         <t>Is the use of a DHT reasonable? Why not MQTT
	 <xref target="MQTT"/> which is well suited for
	 publish-by-one/consume-by-many? What about protocols like protocol buffers? TODO What about dnstap?</t>
      </section>
      <section>
	<name>Packing of messages</name>
	<t>It could be interesting to optimize by packing the data in a C-DNS <xref
      target="RFC8618"/> flow, sent with TCP (with TLS) or
      QUIC. (Of course, other formats/protocols are possible.)</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        
        <xi:include
            href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml"/>
        <xi:include
            href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml"/>
        <xi:include
            href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include
            href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8945.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9499.xml"/>        
      </references>

      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
	<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8020.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8198.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8618.xml"/>
        <xi:include
	    href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/bibxml3/draft-hl-dnsop-cache-filling.xml"/>
        <reference anchor="MQTT" target="https://docs.oasis-open.org/mqtt/mqtt/v5.0/os/mqtt-v5.0-os.docx">
          <front>
            <title>MQTT Version 5.0</title>
            <author>
              <organization>OASIS</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2019"/>
          </front>
        </reference>       
	<!-- https://mqtt.org/mqtt-specification/ -->
      </references>
    </references>
 
        <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>Original idea at the RIPE hackathon in march 2025 at the
      Netnod office in Stockholm.</t>
    </section>
    
 </back>
</rfc>
